<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Web Apps on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</title>
    <link>http://www.edzynda.com/tags/web-apps/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Web Apps on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 Ed Zynda.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.edzynda.com/tags/web-apps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Single Executable Web Apps With Go Binary Assets</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/single-executable-web-apps-with-go-binary-assets/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 07:52:54 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/single-executable-web-apps-with-go-binary-assets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Go is becoming increasingly popular with building web applications. It&amp;rsquo;s fast, lightweight and easy to learn. Another great feature is to compile your applications into a single redistributable binary. A lot of web applications depend on external assets, however. For the application to work you still need to package your css, JavaScript and image files along with the executable. Let&amp;rsquo;s see if we can fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you have a single page web application. Your application code is saved in &lt;code&gt;main.go&lt;/code&gt;. Your frontend code is saved in a folder called &lt;code&gt;assets&lt;/code&gt; and called &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt;. You also have a &lt;code&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt; and a few images. Normally you need to make sure that assets folder exists along side your &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; executable wherever you have it deployed. If not your application will complain with a bunch of &lt;code&gt;404 not found&lt;/code&gt; errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Go, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to convert all of those files to pure Go code and then serve them up like they were sitting on the filesystem. We can accomplish this with two packages &lt;code&gt;jteeuwen/go-bindata&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;elazarl/go-bindata-assetfs&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing we need to do is install the packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ go get github.com/jteeuwen/go-bindata/...
$ go get github.com/elazarl/go-bindata-assetfs/...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can convert our assets to Go code using the &lt;code&gt;go-bindata&lt;/code&gt; CLI tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ go-bindata assets/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a file called &lt;code&gt;bindata.go&lt;/code&gt; in your current directory. All the code in that file will be scoped to the &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; package. To access any of our files we can use the &lt;code&gt;Asset(string) ([]byte, error)&lt;/code&gt; function. Calling &lt;code&gt;Asset(&amp;quot;assets/app.js&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; will return a &lt;code&gt;[]byte&lt;/code&gt; slice of the &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file which we can echo through our web application manually if we wish. An easier method would be to create an endpoint that serves all of those assets as if they were on a fileserver. This is where &lt;code&gt;go-bindata-assetfs&lt;/code&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;package main

import (
	&amp;quot;log&amp;quot;
	&amp;quot;net/http&amp;quot;

	&amp;quot;github.com/elazarl/go-bindata-assetfs&amp;quot;
)

func main() {
	// Use binary asset FileServer
	http.Handle(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;,
		http.FileServer(
			&amp;amp;assetfs.AssetFS{Asset: Asset, AssetDir: AssetDir, AssetInfo: AssetInfo, Prefix: &amp;quot;assets&amp;quot;}))

	log.Println(&amp;quot;http server started on :8000&amp;quot;)
	err := http.ListenAndServe(&amp;quot;:8000&amp;quot;, nil)
	if err != nil {
		log.Fatal(&amp;quot;ListenAndServe: &amp;quot;, err)
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;go-bindata-assetfs&lt;/code&gt; package includes a &lt;code&gt;Struct&lt;/code&gt; type called &lt;code&gt;AssetFS&lt;/code&gt; that implements the &lt;code&gt;http.Filesystem&lt;/code&gt; interface which looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;type FileSystem interface {
        Open(name string) (File, error)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To initialize a new &lt;code&gt;AssetFS&lt;/code&gt; we need to pass a few of the helper functions generated by &lt;code&gt;go-bindata&lt;/code&gt;. The final property is &lt;code&gt;Prefix&lt;/code&gt; which sets the root of the &lt;code&gt;FileServer&lt;/code&gt; as whatever we specify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example we are now serving files at &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; and any files that were in &lt;code&gt;assets/&lt;/code&gt; are now accessible from that path. It would be simple to place an &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file to use as an entrypoint for a single page application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we no longer have to distribute our assets along with the final executable. This makes our deployments just a little bit easier and more managable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>