<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tips on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</title>
    <link>http://www.edzynda.com/categories/tips/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tips on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 Ed Zynda.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.edzynda.com/categories/tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Route/Model Binding In Laravel</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/using-routemodel-binding-in-laravel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/using-routemodel-binding-in-laravel/</guid>
      <description>As I work more and more with Laravel, I keep running across some really cool time saving tricks. One of those time savers is route/model binding.
Let&amp;#8217;s say that you have the following route setup.
&amp;lt;?php Route::get(&#39;books/{book}&#39;, function($book) { return Book::find($book); });  That&amp;#8217;s pretty simple right? Basically you point your browser at /books and then pass a book id and then use the &amp;#8216;Book&amp;#8217; model to fetch that book from the database.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tip: Custom Scripts In WordPress</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/tip-custom-scripts-and-stylesheets-in-wordpress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/tip-custom-scripts-and-stylesheets-in-wordpress/</guid>
      <description>WordPress is a great CMS (Content Management System) is you want to get a site up and running very quickly. It&amp;#8217;s themable and within the theming framework, WordPress includes the ability to include popular assets like JQuery. All it takes is a simple command.
&amp;lt;?php wp_enqueue_script(&#39;jquery&#39;);  What if you don&amp;#8217;t want to use the version of JQuery included in WordPress though? There are several reasons you would require a different version, compatibility for example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tip: Quick Test For XSS Vulnerabilities</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/testing-for-xss-vulnerabilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/testing-for-xss-vulnerabilities/</guid>
      <description>There are a lot of things to keep in mind when it comes to web development. Security should be at the top of your list. If you read up on web application security, you&amp;#8217;re probably familiar with cross-site scripting or XSS attacks. XSS attacks can cause serious damage but are really simple to prevent.
If you aren&amp;#8217;t familiar, a XSS vulnerability occurs when your application takes user data and then sends it to the web browser without proper validation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>