<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Framework on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</title>
    <link>http://www.edzynda.com/tags/framework/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Framework on Ed Zynda - Coder, Hacker, Superhero</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 Ed Zynda.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.edzynda.com/tags/framework/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Test The Untestable With AspectMock</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/test-the-untestable-with-aspectmock/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/test-the-untestable-with-aspectmock/</guid>
      <description>Some of us have had the pleasure of working with someone else&amp;rsquo;s ancient codebase to either add new features or fix bugs. It&amp;rsquo;s never fun and usually a pain. Because of the design (or lack thereof) of the application, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t lend itself to unit testing. The code is littered with static method calls, objects instantiated inside methods rather than being injected through a constructor, and other elements of poor design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Book: Aspect-Oriented Programming in PHP</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/new-book-aspect-oriented-programming-in-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/new-book-aspect-oriented-programming-in-php/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking for a way to challenge myself as well as showcase some of my knowledge to the world. After some thinking, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that I would go ahead and write a book.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a lot about aspect-oriented programming and really like what it provides to enhance object-oriented programming. There isn&amp;rsquo;t a lot of information about this in the PHP community so I figured a book would be a great way to drum up some more interest and help create a larger community around the subject of AOP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aspect Oriented PHP Using Go! AOP Framework</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/aspect-oriented-php-using-go-aop-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/aspect-oriented-php-using-go-aop-framework/</guid>
      <description>In my last article we took a look at using aspect oriented programming (AOP) in PHP by installing the excellent AOP PECL extension for PHP. This is great if you have admin access to the servers you run your code on. It&amp;rsquo;s very common though, for people to run their code on shared hosting. These types of providers don&amp;rsquo;t usually provide a way for you to install any extra PHP extensions besides the common extensions they provide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Is A Microframework? Getting Started With Silex</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/what-is-a-microframework-getting-started-with-silex/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/what-is-a-microframework-getting-started-with-silex/</guid>
      <description>There is no shortage of coding frameworks these days. I can&amp;rsquo;t scroll through my twitter and facebook feeds or my favorite dev forums without stumbling upon something new. Like a hungry barracuda, I&amp;rsquo;m instantly attracted to new shiny things. While browsing reddit.com/r/php I came across a mention of a microframework called Silex. Now you may be wondering what a microframework is. I was wondering the same thing, so I took a look at the project&amp;rsquo;s website to figure out for myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started With Laravel 4 and Vagrant</title>
      <link>http://www.edzynda.com/getting-started-with-laravel-4-and-vagrant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.edzynda.com/getting-started-with-laravel-4-and-vagrant/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with a handful of different PHP frameworks over the years. From ZEND Framework to Codeigniter, all have their pros and cons. Some of them are more difficult to work with than others. None of them, however, have been more enjoyable for me to work with than Laravel.
I came across Laravel while randomly browsing the web. I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember what I was looking for but after reading more about Laravel and how simple it was to setup, I was hooked.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>